<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach">
      Captive Portal ICMP Messages
    </title>
    
    <author fullname="David Bird" initials="D." surname="Bird">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dbird@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="12" month="May" year="2017"/>

    <area>template</area>
    <workgroup>template</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a new ICMP Type for Captive Portal
      Messages. The ICMP Type will only be known to clients supporting
      this specification and provides flow 5-tuple specific
      notifications from the Captive Portal NAS.</t>

      <t>Further, this document defines a multi-part ICMP extension to
      ICMP Destination Unreachable messages to signal, not only that
      the packet was dropped, but that it was dropped due to an Access
      Policy requiring Captive Portal interaction. Legacy clients
      will only be processing the ICMP Destination Unreachable.</t>

      <t>[ Editor note: The IETF is currently discussing improvements in
      captive portal interactions and user experience improvements. See:
      https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/captive-portals ]</t>

      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this before publication. This document is
      being stored in github at
      https://github.com/wlanmac/draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach . Authors
      gratefully accept pull requests, and keep the latest (edit buffer)
      versions there, so commenters can follow along at home.]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Captive Portals work by blocking some and redirecting other
      communications outside of a "walled garden" until the user has
      either authenticated, acknowledged an Acceptable Use Policy
      (AUP), or otherwise satisfied the requirements of the Captive
      Portal.</t>

      <t>Today, notification of captivivity is implemented by
      intercepting HTTP port 80 requests in order for the Captive
      Portal NAS to respond with an HTTP redirect. Depending on the
      captive portal implementation, connections other than HTTP will
      either timeout (silently packets dropped) or meet with a
      different, inaccurate, error condition, for instance a TCP
      reset, for TCP connections, or ICMP Destination Unreachable
      using existing codes. A typical implemenation might reject
      traffic not in the walled garden by returning an ICMP
      Destination Unreachable either Host or Network Administratively
      Prohibited. However, these codes are typically permanent
      policies and do not specifically indicate a captive portal is in
      use.</t>

      <t>This document defines a new ICMP Type for Captive Portal. The
      Captive Portal ICMP Type can be used to send flow 5-tuple
      specific notifications to user devices. As a new ICMP type, it
      is expected to be ignored by legacy devices.</t>

      <t>This document also defines an Extension Object that can be
      appended to selected multi-part ICMP messages to inform the user
      device that they are behind a captive portal, in addition to the
      underlying ICMP information. Devices able to understand the
      extension get extra information about the captive portal access
      policy, whereas legacy devices just understand the underlying
      ICMP message.</t>

      <t>The Captive Portal and Destination Unreachable types provide
      the Captive Portal NAS options in terms of what notifications
      legacy devices can and should understand.</t>

      <t>The Captive Portal ICMP Messages only provide
      notification. They do not provide any configuration. For that,
      we use <xref target="RFC7710"/> and the Captive Portal URI it
      provides.</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
	<t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Capport ICMP device">Device or operating system
          compliant to this specification.</t>
          <t hangText="Legacy device">Device or operating system not
          compliant to this specification.</t>
          <t hangText="Captive Portal NAS">Network Access Server
          implementing Captive Portal enforcement.</t>
          <t hangText="Capport NAS">A Captive Portal NAS supporting
          Capport standards.</t>
	</list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Captive Portal ICMP">
      <t>Captive Portal ICMP messages come in two flavors. Messages
      can be sent using the Captive Portal ICMP Type or they can be
      sent as an ICMP Extension to an existing ICMP Type, such as
      Destination Unreachable. Data is encoded into the packet slightly
      differently in each case, however, the field formats remain
      consistent. All fields are in network byte order.</t>
      
      <t>Capport ICMP devices MUST support <xref
      target="RFC7710"/>.</t>

      <section title="Session-ID">
        <t>An unsigned short session identifier that groups ICMP
        messages. ICMP messages containing the same value MUST be
        assumed to be part of the same access policy. Any change in
        this value between ICMP messages from the same source IP
        address MUST be considered by the client to mean a change in
        access policy has occurred and previous notifications are no
        longer valid.</t>

	<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	   0                   1           
	   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |          Session-ID           |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	
      </section>
      <section title="Flags">
	<t>In Captive Portal ICMP Messages, a flags field contains bit
	flags for optional payload data fields. The Flags field
	provides future extensibility.</t>
	
	<t>Bit flags and their respective data fields:</t>
	
	<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |    Reserved   |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ]]></artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>
      <section title="Message Code/C-Type">
        <t>Captive Portal Message Code and C-Types:
	<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="1">Capport Required (packet dropped)</t>
          <t hangText="2">Capport Suggested - QoS Overflow (packet
          dropped)</t>
          <t hangText="3">Capport Suggested - Warning (packet not
          dropped)</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Message Type">
	<t>The Captive Portal ICMP Type message is specifically for
	Capport ICMP Compliant devices. It is expected that Legacy
	devices will ignore such messages.</t>

	<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	   0                   1                   2                   3
	   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |      Type     |      Code     |          Checksum             |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |      Flags    |     Length    |          Session-ID           |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |      Internet Header + leading octets of original datagram    |
	  |                                                               |
	  |                           //                                  |
	  |                                                               |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ~             Optional Extensions defined by Flags              ~
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ]]></artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>As shown in the figure above, the Captive Portal Flags and
	Session-ID are part of the ICMP header. The optional fields
	are in the ICMP payload, past the required original datagram
	headers of a length defined by Length.</t>

	<t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Length">Number of 4 byte words of original datagram.</t>
	</list></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Extension Object">
	<t>This document defines an extension object that can be
	appended to selected multi-part ICMP messages (<xref
	target="RFC4884"/>). This extension permits the Capport NAS to
	inform Capport ICMP Compliant devices that their connection
	has been blocked due to an Access Policy requiring interaction
	with the Captive Portal.</t>
	
	<t>The Captive Portal Extension Object can be appended to the
	ICMP Destination Unreachable messages. When Legacy devices
	receive such messages, they will only understand the
	Destination Unreachable, ignoring the extensions.</t>

	<t>When used in an Extension Object, the Captive Portal ICMP
	data fields are packed into an extension structure as shown
	below.</t>
	
	<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	   0                   1                   2                   3
	   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |     Flags    |    Reserved    |         Session-ID            |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ~             Optional Extensions defined by Flags              ~
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	
	<t>The following figure depicts the Destination Unreachable
	message with Captive Portal Extension. It must be preceded by
	an ICMP Extension Structure Header and an ICMP Object
	Header. Both are defined in <xref target="RFC4884"/>.</t>
	
	<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	   0                   1                   2                   3
	   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |     Type      |      Code     |          Checksum             |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |     unused    |    Length-A   |         Next-Hop MTU*         |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |      Internet Header + leading octets of original datagram    |
	  |                                                               |
	  |                           //                                  |
	  |                                                               |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |Version|       Reserved        |           Checksum            |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |             Length-B          |   Class-Num   |   C-Type      |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  |     Flags    |    Reserved    |         Session-ID            |
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ~             Optional Extensions defined by Flags              ~
	  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	  ]]></artwork>
	</figure>
	
	<t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type">Set to 3 for Destination Unreachable.</t>
          <t hangText="Code">Can be any value Code value for Type.</t>
          <t hangText="Length-A">Length, in 4 byte words, of original datagram.</t>
          <t hangText="Version">Set to version 2, per RFC 4884.</t>
          <t hangText="Length-B">Length of extension.</t>
          <t hangText="Class-Num">Set to Captive Portal Class-Num.</t>
          <t hangText="C-Type">See section 2.4.</t>
          <t hangText="Flags">Extension for future use.</t>
          <t hangText="Session-ID">See section 2.1.</t>
	</list></t>
	
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to assign a Captive Portal ICMP Message
      Type, as well as Code values defined in section 2.6..</t>

      <t>The IANA is also requested to assign a Class-Num identifier
      for the Captive Portal Extension Object from the ICMP Extension
      Object Classes and Class Sub-types registry.</t>

      <t>The IANA is also requested to form and administer the corresponding
      class sub-type (C-Type) space per section 2.6.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The newly defined ICMP extension mearly annotates existing
      ICMP Destination Unreachable messages to inform users why their
      connection was blocked. This technique can be used to inform
      captive portal detection probe software that a captive portal,
      specifically, is the reason traffic is blocked. Together with
      RFC 7710 providing configuration in the form of Captive Portal
      URL, Capport ICMP provides an improvement over the current
      man-in-the-middle approach to notification and enforcement of
      captive portals.</t>
      <t>The newly defined ICMP Type for Capport is a non-terminal
      message from the network that poses no additional threat over
      existing ICMP connection terminating messages. While Capport
      ICMP may present a new kind of annoyance for the user, this can
      be mitigated by intelligent capport detection software.
      Moreover, the other option the NAS has is to terminate
      connections and enforce the captive portal, which is arguably
      more annoying.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank the members of the capport mailing
      list, Dave Dolson, Vincent van Dam, Martin Thomson, Erik Kline,
      Kyle Larose, and the authors of RFC4950 (especially Ron
      Bonica).</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1122'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0792'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4884'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3986'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7710'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>
      
      <t>From -02 to 03.</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Removed optional flag definitions to be defined later.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t>From -01 to 02.</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Added a new ICMP Type, redefined message payload and
        flags, and introduces Codes/C-Types.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t>From -00 to 01.</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Changed the Captive Portal URL to a URI, and specificed that this
        can ONLY contain a path element, which is appended to
        http://&lt;gateway_ip&gt;. This is to prevent hijacking connections
        to other addresses.</t>
	
        <t>Then removed the entire URL / URI scheme entirely.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t>From -genesis to -00.</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Initial text.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
