<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" ".//reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<!-- WK: Set category, IPR, docName -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <!-- WK: Set long title. -->

    <title abbrev="draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach">Captive Portal ICMP
    Destination Unreachable</title>

    <author fullname="David Bird" initials="D." surname="Bird">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dbird@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>

          <city>Mountain View, CA</city>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="29" month="April" year="2015"/>

    <area>template</area>

    <workgroup>template</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a multi-part ICMP extension to ICMP Destination
      Unreachable messages to signal that a user is behind a Captive
      Portal.</t>

      <t>[ Editor note: The IETF is currently discussing improvements in
      captive portal interactions and user experience improvements. See:
      https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/captive-portals ]</t>

      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this before publication. This document is
      being stored in github at
      https://github.com/wkumari/draft-wkumari-capport-icmp-unreach . Authors
      gratefully accept pull requests, and keep the latest (edit buffer)
      versions there, so commenters can follow along at home.]</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Captive Portals work by blocking (or redirecting) communications
      outside of a "walled garden" until the user has authenticated and / or
      acknowledged an Acceptable Use Policy (AUP). Depending on the captive
      portal implementation, connections other than HTTP will either timeout
      (packets dropped) or meet with a different, inaccurate, error condition
      (like a TCP reset or ICMP Destination Unreachable with existing
      codes).</t>

      <t>A current option for captive portal networks is to reject traffic not
      in the walled garden returning the Destination Unreachable either Host
      or Network Administratively Prohibited. However, these codes are
      typically permanent policies and do not specifically indicate a captive
      portal is in use.</t>

      <t>This document defines an extension object that can be appended to
      selected multi-part ICMP messages to inform the user that they are
      behind a captive portal. This informs the user after they have attempted
      an initial connection and is generated by the Captive Portal NAS
      itself.</t>

      <t>[ Editor note: This is complementary, but solves a different problem
      to: https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-wkumari-dhc-capport-12 -
      wkumari-dhc-capport provides information from a DHCP server (and so
      doesn't need any changes to deployed CPs), and provides information
      *before* the client attempts a connection. It does not, however, have a
      way of noting that an existing connection has been interrupted.]</t>

      <section title="Requirements notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="ICMP Dest Unreachable Captive Portal Object">
      <t>This document defines an extension object that can be appended to
      selected multi-part ICMP messages (<xref target="RFC4884"/>). This
      extension permits Captive Portal (CP) NAS devices to inform user devices
      that their connection has been blocked by the Captive Portal NAS.</t>

      <t>The Dest Unreachable Captive Portal Object can be appended to the
      ICMP Destination Unreachable messages. Figure 1 depicts the Dest
      Unreachable Captive Portal Object. It must be preceded by an ICMP
      Extension Structure Header and an ICMP Object Header. Both are defined
      in <xref target="RFC4884"/>.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |W|  Reserved   |         Validity (seconds)                    |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="W  - 1 bit">Warning. Indicates that the Validity refers
          to when the service will be interrupted. Note that the
          &ldquo;offending&rdquo; traffic was forwarded, not dropped.</t>

          <t hangText="Validity - 24 bits">Time, in seconds, that this result
          should be considered valid (and the OS should not attempt to access
          the same resource in the meantime).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Editor note / questions. We are trying to get some feedback on A:
      this general idea and B: this implementation.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>Some open questions.</t>

          <t hangText="W bit or C-Type">We have currently specified a single
          bit (W) to indicate that the remaining lease time is running low,
          and the the connection will be interrupted sometime "soon". We
          could, instead, use a differnt C-Type. I think a bit is cleaner (and
          we have reserved 7 bits for future flags), but could be convinced
          (or, better yet, bribed) I'm wrong. Or that the whole "warning" idea
          is a bad one...</t>

          <t hangText="Legacy interaction">If we *do* return e.g ICMP
          Destination Unreachable, Communication Administratively Prohibited
          to a "legacy" (non-Dest Unreachable Captive Portal Object aware)
          client with the 'W' bit set, what happens? In the testing I did,
          nothing bad seemed to happen, but I *could* see that some hosts may
          stop sending to that address, or...</t>

          <t hangText="General concept">Is this idea useful?</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to assign a Class-Num identifier for the Dest
      Unreachable Captive Portal Object from the ICMP Extension Object Classes
      and Class Sub-types registry.</t>

      <t>The IANA is also requested to form and administer the corresponding
      class sub-type (C-Type) space, as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t>Dest Unreachable Captive Portal Sub-types:</t>

          <t hangText="0">Reserved.</t>

          <t hangText="1">This message format.</t>

          <t hangText="0x02-0xF6 ">Available for assignment</t>

          <t hangText="0xF7-0xFF">Reserved for private use</t>
        </list> C-Type values are assignable on a first-come-first-serve
      (FCFS) basis.</t>

      <t>[ Editor note: Currently we are not using the C-Type for anything,
      but I filled this in anyway. Probably we would overload it at a version
      identifier type thing, but it could also allow further extension, for
      example, a pointer to a status page. ]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This method simply annotates existing ICMP Destination Unreachable
      messages to inform users why their connection was blocked. This
      technique can be used to inform captive portal detection probe software
      that there is a captive portal present (and potentially to connect to
      the URL handed out using draft-wkumari-dhc-capport. We anticipate that
      there will be a new solution devised (such as a well known URL / URI on
      captive portals) to allow the user / captive portal probe to do
      sometyhing more useful with this information.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank the Yaron Sheffer and the authors of
      RFC4950 (especially Ron Bonica ) - I stole much of his text when writing
      the extension definition.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1122'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0792'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4884'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3986'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-iana-objects-03.xml'?>
    </references>

    <section title="Changes / Author Notes.">
      <t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section before publication ]</t>

      <t>From -00 to 01.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Changed the Captive Portal URL to a URI, and specificed that this
          can ONLY contain a path element, which is appened to
          http://&lt;gateway_ip&gt;. This is to prevent hijacking connections
          to other addresses.</t>

          <t>Then removed the entire URL / URI scheme entirely.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>From -genesis to -00.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Initial text.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
